Guide to the Douglas Engelbart Symposia Records
Stanford University Libraries.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives.
Douglas Engelbart symposia records
1998, 2008
SC0561
Stanford University
6.5 Linear feet 5 boxes, 11 DVDs
The materials consist of videorecordings, brochures and handouts from the symposia, clippings, press releases, press kit, photographs from the event, and a videotape of TV coverage from various news shows.
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives. Stanford University Libraries. 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Stanford University Libraries in conjunction with the Institute for the Future presented on December 9, 1998 a celebration of the 30th anniversary of Douglas Engelbart's invention of the computer mouse.
Description of the Collection
The materials consist of videorecordings, brochures and handouts from the event, clippings, press releases, press kit, photographs from the event, and a videotape of TV coverage from various news shows.
Access Terms
Engelbart's unfinished revolution (1998: Stanford, Calif.); Engelbart, D. C., 1925-; Computers--History.; Computers--Technological innovations.; Videorecordings.
Collection Contents
- "Engelbart's Unfinished Revolution" records, 1998 Dec 9; Accession ARCH-1999-073 (Box 1)
  Brochures and handouts from the symposia, clippings, press releases, press kit, and photographs from the event.
  On December 9th, 1998 Stanford University Libraries and the Institute for the Future presented a day-long, public symposium that brought together Engelbart and members of his historic team, along with other computer visionaries, to consider the impact of Engelbart's work on the last three decades of the computer revolution, to explore the challenges facing us today, and to speculate about the next three decades.
- "Engelbart's Unfinished Revolution" videorecordings, 1998 Dec 9; Accession ARCH-2005-231
  - Session 1, 1998; 561.2; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 2)
    Session 1: 9:00-10:40 Morning
    9:00 Greeting and Introductions from Condoleezza Rice, Michael A. Keller, Paul Saffo (Moderator) 9:15 Panel Discussion on the 1968 Demo: Engelbart, Brand, English, Irby, Rulifson 10:15 Tim Lenoir
    - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2U)
  - Session 2, 561.3; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 2)
    Session 2: 11:00-12:40 Morning
    11:00 Panel Discussion on the Last 30 Years: Andreessen, Caruso, Nielson, Rheingold, Zappacosta 11:40 Alan Kay 12:10 Panel Discussion on New Horizons: Card, Drexler, Evans, Horn, Markoff
    - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 3U)
  - Session 3a, 561.4; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 2)
    Session 3: 2:00-3:30 Afternoon
    2:00 Unfinished Revolution Conversation: Engelbart, Rulifson 2:30 Ted Nelson 3:00 Andy van Dam
    - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 4U)
  - Session 3b, 561.5; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP) (Box 2)
    - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 5U)
  - Session 4, 561.6; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 2)
    Session 4: 3:50-5:30 Afternoon
    3:50 Terry Winograd 4:20 Stewart Brand 4:50 Jaron Lanier 5:20 Closing Remarks 5:30 Adjourn
    - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 6U)
  - 1968 Presentation Highlights, 561.7; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP) (Box 2)
    Highlighs from December 9, 1968 presentation during which Doug Engelbart and a small team of researchers from the Stanford Research Institute stunned the computing world with an extraordinary demonstration at a San Francisco computer conference. They debuted: the computer mouse, graphical user interface, display editing and integrated text and graphics, hyper-documents, and two-way video-conferencing with shared workspaces. These concepts and technologies were to become the cornerstones of modern interactive computing.
    That landmark 1968 demonstration took place at the American Federation of Information Processing Societies' Fall Joint Computer Conference. At a time when computers were little more than huge number-crunchers, Engelbart and his team's introduction of their two-way interactive system, called NLS (for oN Line System) was a shock.
    Today the mouse, graphical user interface, hyper-documents, display editing and integrated text and graphics are taken for granted. Other features of NLS, such two-way video-conferencing with shared workspaces, remain more vision than reality even today. And some of NLS' most important elements, such as the concept of bootstrapping, remain so novel that they are all but unknown to the current generation of systems designers.
    NLS' 1968 demo was a watershed that fundamentally changed the trajectory of the computing revolution, contributing not only ideas, but also many of the people who would later build the systems we would use today. Alumni of the NLS project (and its successor, the Augment project) include many of the most influential figures in Silicon Valley (and elsewhere). Others credit Doug's work in general, and the 1968 demo in particular with influencing their design philosophies. As personal computing pioneer and visionary Alan Kay once observed, "I don't know what Silicon Valley will do when it runs out of Doug's ideas."
    - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 7U)
  - Video roll-ins, 561.8; 1 videotape(s) (Betacam-SP L) (Box 2)
    - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
    - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 8U)
  - News clips re: 30th anniversary of the mouse, 1998 Dec 6-13; 561.9; 1 videotape(s) (VHS) (Box 2)
    CBS This Morning (3:27); Newscenter Four Nightbeat (:48); ZDTV Network News(5:05); The Screen Savers (7:20); Silicon Valley Business (4:26; 1:23); Fox X-Press (:17)
- "Boosting Collective IQ" videorecordings and slides, 2008 Aug 4-22; Accession ARCH-2011-080
  In August 2008 the Doug Engelbart Institute sponsored an extended three way discussion between leading experts Doug Engelbart, Jeff Rulifson, and Christina Engelbart, drilling down into the depths of Doug's vision using the Bootstrap "Paradigm Map" interactive slide presentation. This informal discussion, spanning four days, was filmed in a TV studio at Stanford University.
  The Bootstrap "Paradigm Map" is Doug Engelbart's interactive visual portrayal of his call to action, depicting his vision and strategy for dramatically raising our Collective IQ toward more effective organizations and a better world.
  - Videorecordings
    - Session 1 of 4, 2008 Aug 4; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 2)
      From the Bootstrap Dialogs Project – Doug Engelbart, Jeff Rulifson, and Christina Engelbart discuss the Bootstrap "Paradigm Map" in-depth at Stanford Video - Stanford University's television studios.
      - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
      - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 1U)
    - Session 2 of 4, 2008 Aug 6; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 2)
      - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
      - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 2U)
    - Session 3 of 4, 2008 Aug 8; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 2)
      - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
      - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 3U)
    - Session 4 of 4, 2008 Aug 22; 1 videotape(s) (DVCAM) (Box 2)
      - Duplicating master, 1 computer file(s) (MP4)
      - Use copy, 1 optical disc(s) (DVD) (Box 4U)
  - Slides
    - PDF format minus the animation
    - PowerPoint slideshow with animation
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2015-075
  - Posters - "30th Anniversary of the Mouse" (2), 1998; 24 x 36 inches (Box 1)
    "To improve our collective ability to solve the world's problems, we must harness the immense promise and power of technology. the mouse is just a first step; Douglas c. Engelbart - Father of the mouse; 1968-1998; 30th anniversary of the mouse; Logitech."
- Additional Material, Accession ARCH.2015-123
  - Posters - "Engelbart's Unfinished Revolution" (2), 1998 Dec 9 (Box 1)
General note
Contact Public Services (e-mail: speccollref@stanford.edu) for information on accessing digital objects in this collection.